[Otohime's plan strikes Edo!! The Treasure
Box G turns everyone old.]
[Soldiers from Ryugu Palace chase after Shinpachi and the others!! In such a desperate situation, Gintoki and Katsura are...]
["The Older, The Wiser"]
(新八)これこれ｡
この洞窟なんて 使えないですか？
This is it. You think we
can use this cave?
とりあえず 雨露は しのげますよ｡
It'll at least put a roof over our heads.
骸骨 ありますけど…｡
There's a skeleton, though.
(九兵衛)ﾎﾞｸらと同じく➡
These are the remains of someone
who drifted to this island like we did.
この島に 漂着した者の
なれの果てか…｡
早く 脱出の方法を講じねば➡
If we don't come up with a plan to
escape soon, we'll end up like that.
ﾎﾞｸらも いずれ…｡
(足音)
Huh? Shinpachi-san?
(亀梨)あれ？ 新八さん？
か… 亀梨さん!?
K-Kamenashi-san?!
いや～ 捜し…｡
I've been looking for you...
Don't give me that! Where the hell
have you been, you stupid turtle?!
捜したじゃねえだろうが お前！
ｺﾗ～!!
今まで
どこに 行ってやがったんだ～！
この どん亀が～!!
あっ… 痛い… ちょっと離して！
Ow. Hey, let go...
恩を 仇で返しやがって！
How dare you repay my
kindness with ill will!
なにが 竜宮城に連れていくだ！
You were going to take
us to Ryugu Palace?!
ｱﾝﾀのせいでな
ｵﾚたちは こんな無人島に…！
Because of you, we're stuck
on this deserted island!
新八君！ 落ち着け！
えっ？
Shinpachi-kun, calm down.
Huh? Hey... What are you
saying? Deserted island?
ちょっと なに 言ってんすか？
無人島って…｡
無人島だろうが～!!
This is a deserted island! How could
you do this? There's nothing here!
どうしてくれんだ！
こんな 何も ないところで～!!
えっ？
無人島じゃないっすよ ここ｡
Huh? This isn't a deserted Island.
This is Ryugu Palace.
竜宮城です｡
な… なに わけ わかんねえこと
言ってんだ ｺﾗ～!!
Wh-What the hell kind of nonsense
are you taking about?!
言うに事欠いて お前 ｺﾗ～!!
Of all the things to say!
If this is Ryugu Palace, then my toilet
is also Ryugu Palace, damn it!
ここが 竜宮城だったらな➡
ｳﾁの便所も 竜宮城だ ｺﾗ～!!
落ち着け 新八君！
ｷﾐの家の厠が 竜宮城なら➡
Calm down, Shinpachi-kun!
If your toilet is Ryugu Palace, is it okay to say
that my microwave is also Ryugu Palace?
ｳﾁの 電子ﾚﾝｼﾞも
竜宮城と 言っていいのか？
いいかな？ 言っても…｡
知らねえよ！
I can say that, right?
I don't care!
≪(お妙)新ちゃ～ん！
Shin-chan...
(お妙)何か あったの？
姉上～！
Did you find something?
Sis!
食糧 見つけました～！
We found food! Today, we'll
be dining on turtle stew!
今日は 亀鍋です！
まぁ～！
Oh my.
待って待って 待って！
ﾏｼﾞっすって！
Wait, wait, wait! I'm serious!
This is Ryugu Palace!
ここ 竜宮城なんですって！
I swear on kelp! No, I swear on seaweed!
昆布に誓っても いいっすわ！
いや！ ﾜｶﾒに誓います！
同じようなもんだろうが～!!
That's pretty much the same thing!
Shinpachi-kun, Shinpachi-kun...
(九兵衛)新八君 新八君…｡
なに！
What is it?
あっ…｡
[Ryugu Palace, 3-chome, 2-5-3]
いや～ でも よかったっすわ｡
皆さん ご無事で…｡
Well, I'm really glad that everyone's safe.
まさか 皆さん ﾎﾞｸの家の近所に
流れ着いてるとは…｡
I never expected you guys would
wash up near my house.
えぇぇぇぇ～っ!?
ちょっ… 待っ… えぇぇぇ～っ!?
What?! Hey, wait! What?!
りゅ… りゅうぐうじゃう…
これ 竜宮城!?
R-Ryugu Palace! This is Ryugu Palace?!
えぇ… まぁ…
竜宮城といっても あれっすよ｡
Yes. Well, this IS Ryugu Palace,
but this is the very outskirts of it.
ｷﾞﾘｷﾞﾘ 竜宮城の端｡
Pretty much near Saitama prefecture.
どっちかっていうと
埼玉寄りですけどね｡
ｳ… ｳｿだ～!!
N-No way!
Then how do you explain that?!
じゃあ あれは
どう 説明 つけんだよ!!
竜宮城で
死亡者 出てるだろうが～！
There's a dead body in Ryugu Palace!
No matter how I look at it, that was
someone who got lost at sea here!
あれ どう見ても
遭難者だろうが～!!
Oh, this is my wife.
(亀梨)あぁ… これ？
ｳﾁの嫁さんっすね｡
えぇぇぇ～っ!? 嫁さん!?
これ 嫁さんなの～!?
What?! Your wife?! This is your wife?!
(亀梨)死んでないっすよ｡
産卵期は ｴﾈﾙｷﾞｰ 使って➡
She's not dead.
She just gets really tired when she's laying
eggs and tends to grow very thin.
だいぶ 痩せちゃうんすよ｡
動かなくなるし…｡
She even stops moving.
痩せるって 完全に
骸骨に なってんだろうが～!!
Thin? She's a skeleton!
みどり 皆さんに ご挨拶しなさい｡
Midori, say hello to everyone.
あ～ すいませんね…｡
Sorry, my wife is a bit shy.
ｼｬｲなもんで… ｳﾁの嫁…｡
She's not shy. She's a lot of things
but shy isn't one of them!
ｼｬｲじゃねえだろう！
いろんなもん➡
赤裸々に 剥き出しだろう！
[Save me...]
(亀梨)もう～
また ﾌﾛｰﾘﾝｸﾞ 傷つけて…｡
Shoot, you scratched up the floor again?
(亀梨)しようがないな…｡
予定日まで あと ひと月か｡
Oh well...
One more month until the due date,
huh? I understand your suffering.
(亀梨)わかってるから
お前の苦しみは｡
(亀梨)ﾎﾞｸも 協力するから
丈夫な卵 産もうな！
I'll help you out. Just lay
some healthy eggs.
She's beyond help!
どんだけ 紛らわしいﾒｯｾｰｼﾞ!?
ちゃんと 甲羅 被って 寝ないと
ﾀﾞﾒだって～｡
Make sure you put your shell
on when you sleep.
What's the meaning of this?
(九兵衛)これは どういうことだ？
とりあえず 本当に
無人島じゃないみたいです｡
Anyway, it seems that this
isn't a deserted island.
(長谷川)それじゃあ ｵﾚたち
普通の生活に 帰れるのか？
Does that mean we can return
to our normal lives?
All right! We can leave! I'm
sick of Ryugu Palace!
やった～!! 帰れる！
もう 竜宮城なんて うんざりだ！
We had a lot of complications, but I'll
have no complaints if we can leave!
紆余曲折 あったが
帰れるなら 文句はねえよ！
さっさと こんなところからは
ﾄﾝｽﾞﾗ しようぜ～!!
Let's get out of this place right now.
おい 亀～!!
ｵﾚたちを 早く この島から帰せ！
Hey, turtle! Get us off of this island immediately!
We're sick of this place!
もう うんざりなんだよ
こんな所～!!
帰るって… どこに？
はっ!?
Where will you go back to?
Huh?
帰るところなんて…➡
There's nothing for you
to return to anymore.
もう どこにも ないっすよ｡
♪♪～
Wh-What is that?
(男)な… なんだ あれは!?
Turtles?! An armada of turtles
is headed this way!
(男)亀が… 大量の亀が
こちらに 向かってくる～!!
(女の悲鳴)
Run away!
(男)逃げろ～!!
♪♪～
(男)おい！ なんだ!? あれ！
Hey...
What is that?
♪♪～
(花野ｱﾅ)
ご覧いただけるでしょうか！
Just take a look at the terrible
thing that's happening to Edo.
(花野ｱﾅ)この 江戸の町の惨状を！
(花野ｱﾅ)突如 現れた
亀のような機械から 投下された➡
Machines that look like turtles suddenly appeared
and dropped mysterious boxes.
奇妙な箱！
そこから発せられた ｶﾞｽにより➡
The gas emitted from these boxes is turning
everyone in Edo into old fogies.
江戸の人々が 次々に➡
年老いた 老人のような姿に
変えられていっております！
いったい
何が 起きているのでしょうか？
What's happening?
あの亀は…
あの箱は… あのｶﾞｽは…➡
What exactly are those turtles,
those boxes, and that gas?
いったい 何なのでしょうか!?
Back to the studio.
いったん ｽﾀｼﾞｵに お返しします！
(むせる声)
(草野)花野ｱﾅ｡ これは➡
Hanano announcer, some people claim
that this is some sort of bio-terrorism.
一種の ﾊﾞｲｵﾃﾛとの声も
挙がっているんですが➡
そのへんの情報は
入っているんですか？
Have you received any information
concerning that?
Umm, well... I forgot.
え～っとでしゅね…➡
え～っと…➡
忘れました…｡
花野ｱﾅ？ おかしいですね…➡
Hanano announcer? That's odd.
ちょっと うまく
映像が つながらないようです｡
The video feed doesn't seem
to be coming in very well.
(草野)ばばあ どけ～!!
じゃあ いったん ＣＭ いきます｡
Out of the way old lady! Well, let's
cut to a commercial break for now.
江戸が…
じいさん ばあさんだらけに…｡
Edo's being turned into
a city full of old people!
どういうことなんですか これは！
What's the meaning of this?!
What happened to Edo?
いったい 江戸で
何が 起こっているんですか!?
あれは 竜宮城で開発された
老化促進兵器…➡
That's the Treasure Box G,
a weapon developed in Ryugu
Palace that hastens old age.
玉手箱Ｇ！
竜宮城？ 竜宮城が 江戸に➡
Ryugu Palace?! Ryugu Palace
launched that attack on Edo?!
あんな攻撃を
仕掛けてるんですか？
What's the meaning of this? Isn't
this Ryugu Palace, too?!
どういうことだよ？
ここも 竜宮城じゃねえのかよ！
まさか ﾃﾒｴも敵？
Don't tell me you're an enemy, too!
敵なら こんなところに
わざわざ連れてきたりしないすよ｡
If I was your enemy, I wouldn't have
taken the time to bring you here.
ﾜｶﾒ根本暗しっていうでしょ｡
It's dark at the root of seaweed.
[Note: A parody of the Japanese proverb "It's dark at the base of a lighthouse," which means "People often know little of what is happening right under their noses."]
灯台下暗しでしょ｡ 亀梨さん…➡
You mean, "It's dark at the
base of a lighthouse.
Kamenashi-san, did you bring
us to this island to save us...
まさか あなた… ﾎﾞｸらを➡
あの被害から救うため
こんな島に？
from that disaster?
That's half right and half wrong.
それは
半分当たっていて 半分違うな｡
ｵﾚは… 乙姫の野望を
共に叩き潰す 勇士と見込んで➡
I brought you all here because
I believe you are
the only people who can crush
Otohime and her plan.
ここに ｷﾐたちを呼んだのさ｡
(銃声)
あれは！
Look over there!
(亀兵士)急げ急げ 急げ！
ｸﾞｽﾞｸﾞｽﾞするな！
Hurry up, hurry up, hurry
up! Don't waste time.
この ﾄﾞｼﾞで のろまな亀ども！
ひっくり返されたいのか！
You stupid, slow turtles! Do you want
me to whack you onto your backs?
亀梨～！ 出てきやがれ～！
Kamenashi!! Come on out!
大楼主
親衛隊隊長の身でありながら➡
You're the captain of the brothel
owner's bodyguards!
乙姫様に反旗を翻したこと
万死に値する！
We're going to punish you with death for
starting a revolt against Otohime-sama.
ﾃﾒｴが地球人を
かくまってるのはお見通しだ！
We know you're harboring Earthlings!
All Earthlings are to be annihilated!
すべての地球人は 処分の対象！
地球人ともども 即刻出てこ～い！
All you Earthlings...
Surrender immediately!
Tsk! He's on to me. Let's go.
(亀梨)ﾁｯ 勘づかれたか！ 行くぞ｡
ちょっ… 待って！
いたぞ！
Huh? Hey... Wait!
There he is!
Over there! It's Kamenashi!
あそこだ！ 亀梨だ～!!
(銃声)
うわぁああ～！
ちょっと～ どうなってんですか!?
Hey! What's going on?!
ﾎﾞｸら 夏休みに来たんですけど！
夏休みなんですけど～っ!!
We came here to have
a fun summer vacation!
We're on summer vacation!
平たく言う｡
この星は 竜宮城の主➡
I'll give it to you straight.
Otohime, the ruler of Ryugu Palace,
plans to conquer this planet.
乙姫に狙われている｡
このままいけば この地球は➡
At this rate, Earth will become
a planet full of only the elderly!
じいさんと ばあさんしかいない
星にされるぞ！
ｵﾚは その企みに勘づき
計画を阻止するため➡
I discovered her plan and went
looking for the bravest people
乙姫を叩き潰すことのできる
勇士を探していたんだ！
who could defeat Otohime and her plan!
そのために あえて悪事を働き➡
[Doraimon]
But I was forced into committing
evil deeds while I searched
悪を許せぬ正義の魂を持った
者たちを求めた！
for the right people who had pure
souls and could not tolerate evil!
そう それがｷﾐたちだ！
あえてじゃねえだろう！
Yes! You are those people!
You weren't forced!
嫁さん ほったらかして
なんで 盗撮ﾋﾞﾃﾞｵ…➡
You abandoned your wife.
Why are you running away with
such voyeuristic-looking videos.
大事そうに抱えて逃げてんだ!?
何だ？ どらｲﾓﾝ って！
What's with the "Doraimon" label?! You're
completely trying to disguise them!
完全に ｶﾑﾌﾗｰｼﾞｭだろうが!!
(お妙)どこを見ても亀だらけ！
完全に島を包囲されてるんだわ！
There are turtles everywhere.
We're completely surrounded.
(長谷川)追い込まれてんぞ！
どうすんだ おい！
We've been cornered!! What do we do?!
Crap! Of all times, why are the people
we can rely on the most not here?!
ｸｿ！ こんなときにかぎってなぜ➡
いちばん頼りになる
ﾔﾂらがおらん？
がんばって
もちこたえてください！
Try your best to hold out!
もう少しの辛抱です！
Just a little longer.
あの人たちは
必ず来てくれるはず！
I'm sure they'll come.
おい！ ﾃﾒｴ 何やってんだ！
Hey! What are you doing?
Gin-san will...
《銀さんなら 必ず…》
(銀時)よぉ… 待たせたな｡
Hey, sorry to keep you waiting.
銀さん！
Gin-san...
今から行くからな… 待っとれ…｡
I'm coming right over. Wait for me.
新… 新… 何だっけ？
Shin, Shin...what was it?
(桂)新一郎君じゃ…
大きくなったのう…｡
It's Shinichiro-kun. You've gotten big.
おいで 50円 あげよう…｡
Come here. I'll give you 50 yen.
Umm... Who are these old guys?
え～と… 誰？ その人たち…｡
(神楽)銀ちゃんと ﾂﾞﾗ… ｱﾙ｡
It's Gin-chan and Zura.
ﾂﾞﾗじゃない… ｶ… ｶ… ｯﾍﾟ！
I'm not "Zura." I'm Ka, Ka...
What was I saying?
何だっけ？
I believe you were saying something
about Kamille Bidan.
[Note: Parody of Kamille Bidan from GUNDAM Z.]
ｶﾐｭﾋﾞﾀﾞﾝ… とかなんとか
言っとった気がしたのう…｡
そうじゃ… ｶ ｶ… ｯﾍﾟ！
That's right. Ka, Ka...
まさかｷﾐたち… ｵﾚが 竜宮城から
密かに持ち出してきた➡
Don't tell me you touched the sample
玉手箱Ｇの
ｻﾝﾌﾟﾙに触れたんじゃ…｡
Treasure Box G I snuck
out of Ryugu Palace.
(桂)何じゃ？ ｻﾝﾌﾟﾙって…｡
知らんわ｡
What sample?
I don't know.
つうか
さっきから思っとったけど➡
Anyway, I've been wondering:
Who are you?
お前 誰じゃ？
お前が誰じゃ？
Who are you?
ｳｿｰｯ!!
No way!!
♪♪～
(亀兵士)失礼しまする｡
反旗を翻していた➡
Excuse me.
We have captured the rebellious
former captain of the guard,
亀梨 元親衛隊隊長
他 地球人６名…➡
天人１名を捕縛しました！
Kamenashi, along with six Earthlings
and one Amanto.
Yes. Good work. I commend you. Kamenashi
is to be immediately executed.
(乙姫)うん よくやった｡
褒めてつかわす｡
亀梨は すぐに処刑｡
地球人どもは
すべて 玉手箱にかけい｡
Use a treasure box on the
rest of the Earthlings.
(亀兵士)御意！
Understood.
(乙姫)ﾌﾌﾌ… これで美しき者は
この星より消える｡
Now all the beautiful people
on this planet will disappear.
わらわより美しき者など
この世にはいらぬ｡
I have no need of anyone in this world
who is more beautiful than me.
わらわこそ この世で
いちばん美しき存在｡
I am the most beautiful
creature in the world.
竜宮が主 乙姫なるぞ！
ﾎ～ｯﾎｯﾎｯﾎﾎﾎ…！
I, Otohime, the ruler of Ryugu.
(ﾎｽﾃｽ)ｷｬｰ！ 見て見て！
魚が泳いでるわ！
Look, look! Look at all the fish swimming!
(ﾎｽﾃｽ)あ～ん もう夢みたい！
This is like a dream!
まさか 竜宮城で
夏休みが過ごせるなんてぇ！
I never dreamed of being able to spend
summer vacation at Ryugu Palace!
(阿音)松平のﾀﾞﾝﾅ
ほんと ありがとう！
Pops Matsudaira, thank you so much!
(松平)構うこたぁねえよ｡
This is the life.
ｽﾏｲﾙの皆には いつも…➡
Only you beautiful girls
of Cabaret Smile can wash
away the filth in my world.
浮世の垢を
落としてもらってんだ｡
今日は おじさんが 皆に
ｻｰﾋﾞｽしちゃうからして➡
I'll be the one who serves you today.
好きなだけ遊びやがれ～！
Have as much fun as you like.
ｷｬ～ 松ちゃん 大好き！
Matchan, I love you!
(松平)よっしゃ おらぁ～
ﾄﾞﾝﾍﾟﾘ 持ってこい～！
All right! Bring me some Dom Perignon!
(花子)つうか
竜宮城でも ｽﾅｯｸでも➡
He's not doing anything here that
he doesn't do at the hostess club.
やってること変わらへんな｡
He's apparently a VIP member.
(おりょう)VIP会員らしいわよ｡
毎年 夏は ここで
過ごしてるんだって｡
He always spends his summers here.
Celebrities really are spoiled.
やっぱ ｾﾚﾌﾞは違うわ｡
ﾎﾝﾏ お妙ちゃんも
来ればよかったのになぁ｡
That's so true. Otae-chan should
have come with us.
連絡つかないのよ｡
何やってんのかしら あの子｡
I can't get in touch with her.
I wonder what she's doing.
(花子)竜宮城なんて
なかなか来られるもんちゃうで｡
It's not every day you get
to come to Ryugu Palace.
(おりょう)ﾎﾝﾄ おとぎ話の
産物だとばかり思ってたけどね｡
That's true. I thought it was just
the product of a folktale.
(花子)要するに 知る人ぞ知る
超高級ﾘｿﾞｰﾄ地やねんな？
It's really just a super exclusive
luxury resort, isn't it?
After all, Urashima-han had fun here
until he became an old man.
[Note: Hanako is talking with an Osaka accent.]
そら 浦島はんも おじいなるまで
遊びまくるっちゅう話や｡
(おりょう)
私たちも ほどほどにしないとね｡
We shouldn't overdo it.
そんな 甘っちょろい
(舌打ち)
所じゃねえよ ここは｡
Tsk, tsk, tsk. This place isn't
such an easygoing place.
竜宮城は もともと
惑星国家間を股にかける➡
Ryugu Palace used to be a
giant mobile luxury brothel.
移動式巨大高級妓楼だったのよ｡
It used to travel between planet nations.
It doesn't belong to any country.
どこの国にも属さない
超法規的機関として➡
As an organization that
is beyond the law,
多くの権力者の寵愛を受け
瞬く間に 巨大な力を手に入れた｡
it's received many favors
from powerful people
and has gained enormous influence.
今や 一国家と
互角の力を有する動く城➡
Right now, it's a moving palace,
no, a city-state that has as much
power as a single country.
いや 動く都市国家だ｡
そんな巨大な力をもってる城が
なんで こんな島国の海に➡
Why does a palace with that much
power stay in these waters?
沈んどんのや？
えっ？ それはな…｡
Huh? Well...
あぁ～ ちょっと待って｡
[TEL]
Uh, hold on a second.
はいはい もしもし… あん？
今 竜宮城だ｡
Hello? Huh? I'm at Ryugu
Palace right now.
Ah! The Dom Perignon is here!
(ﾎｽﾃｽ)きゃ～ ﾄﾞﾝﾍﾟﾘきたわよ！
何かしら これ… わっ！
What could this be?
Huh?
(松平)あん？ 江戸じゅうが
年寄りだらけになってる？
Edo has been turned into a
city full of elderly chumps?
何 わけ わからねえこと
言ってるんだ おい！
What kind of nonsense
are you talking about?
老人にされた人たちが
次々に運びこまれてくる｡
They're still bringing in the people
who have been turned old.
いずれ ﾎﾞｸたちも…｡
We're going to become like that, too.
何のつもりか知らんが
本当に乙姫とやらは➡
I'm not sure what she's up to,
but it looks like Otohime really wants to
turn this country into nothing
but old people.
この国を老人だらけに
するつもりらしいな｡
どうするんだよ！
亀は どっか違うところ➡
What are we going to do?
The turtle was taken somewhere else,
連れてかれちまったし
身動きは とれねえし…｡
we can't move, and those
two are still like that.
ｺｲﾂらは こんなんだし…｡
つうか 何で ｺｲﾂら
１日中 相撲ばっかり観てんの？
Why have they been watching
sumo all day?
[Note: Elderly people in Japan like to watch sumo.]
何で 牢屋にﾃﾚﾋﾞがあるの!?
Why is there a TV in this cell?
銀ちゃん
なに食べてるｱﾙか？ それ…｡
Gin-chan, what are you eating?
いや 食べてないから
それ 歯がないだけ｡
He's not eating. He just
doesn't have any teeth.
１人で こっそり
なに食べてるﾈ それ｡
What are you secretly
eating by yourself?
He's not eating anything.
いや 食べてないって それ！
よこせよ～！
Give it to me!
I want to eat it, too!
私も食べたい！
神楽ちゃん！ 食べてないから!!
Kagura-chan, he's not eating anything!
それ つうか
口に入ってるもん 食う気かよ！
And were you really going to
eat what was in his mouth?!
よこせよ！
やかましいわ！
Hand it over!
Shut up! Why are you
making such a fuss?!
何を騒いどるんじゃ お前たちは！
ｳﾁにばかり こもってないで➡
Don't just stay indoors all day.
子供は 外で遊ばんか！ ﾊﾞｶﾓﾝが!!
Children should play outside,
you lazy bums!
じゃあ 鉄格子 外せ ｸｿじじい！
Then get rid of the iron bars, you old fart!
I want to... I want to eat it, too!
(神楽)私も 私も食べたい！
まったく近頃の若い者は
やれ ﾌｧﾐﾘｰｺﾝﾋﾟｭｰﾀｰだ➡
Honestly. Young people these days...
They have their Family Computers
and their Mega Drives...
[Note: Family Computer (Famicom) = NES.
Mega Drive = Sega Master System.]
やれ ﾒｶﾞﾄﾞﾗｲﾌﾞだ
ｳﾁにばかり こもりおって｡
They stay in the house all the time.
全部 ﾁｮｲｽが古いんですけど…｡
All of your examples are old.
ﾜｼらが若い頃にはのう 銀時
暇さえあれば➡
When Gintoki and I were young,
we would run around the mountains and only
play with our Mega Drives in our free time.
野山を駆け回って
ﾒｶﾞﾄﾞﾗｲﾌﾞしたもんじゃ｡
最終的に
お前らもやってんじゃねえか！
In the end, you played with them, too!
Zura, you...
ﾂﾞﾗ… お前…｡
最終的に お前も
ﾒｶﾞﾄﾞﾗｲﾌﾞしてんじゃねえか…｡
In the end you played with
the Mega Drive, too.
突っ込みおせぇよ！
どんだけ たっぷり➡
You took way too long to comment!
How long of a pause do you need?!
間をつかってんですか！
もう それﾎﾞｸ突っ込みましたから➡
I already commented on that.
無理しなくていいですから
ﾎﾞｸに 任せといてください｡
You don't need to push yourself.
Just leave it to me.
年寄り扱いするんじゃねえよ！
Don't treat me like an old geezer.
まだまだ 若い者には負けんわい｡
I still won't lose to you young folks.
長谷川 銀時 だいたい
近頃の若い者の 突っ込みには➡
As I would have expected
of you, Gintoki.
Young people are so rude
and unrefined these days.
わび さびがないわい
ﾜｼらが 若い頃は…｡
When we were young...
おい うぜぇよ ｺｲﾂら
もう次ﾎﾞｹても 絶対無視しようぜ｡
These guys are really annoying!
Let's ignore them the next time
they say something silly.
どうしたものか まったくの
老人になってしまっている…｡
What on earth happened?
They've completely became old geezers.
なんとか
元に戻す方法は ないですかね？
Do you think there's a way
to turn them back?
We probably have to ask
Otohime in person.
直接 乙姫に会って
聞き出すしかないだろう｡
素直に教えてくれるとは
思えんが…｡
I don't think she'll just tell us, though.
別に このままでも
いいんじゃない？
It's not a big deal if we leave
them like this, is it?
もともと こんなもの
だったでしょう 銀さんて｡
Gin-san was always like this, wasn't he?
No, he was a little brighter, Sis.
いやいやいや…
もうちょっと ﾏｼだったよ 姉上｡
いやいや こんなものだろう
もともと 白髪みてえなもんだし➡
No, he was kind of like this.
He's always had white hair and
he's been kind of like this
放送３年目に入ったら
これくらいになるよ｡
since we've been on the
air for three years.
You are all just as lazy as him!
ｵﾒｴら ただ動くの
面倒くせぇだけだろ！
おい｡
あぁ もういいですから！
Hey...
It's all right. I already commented,
so you don't need to say anything.
もう突っ込みましたから
もう いいですから｡
最終的に お前も
ﾒｶﾞﾄﾞﾗｲﾌﾞしてんじゃねえか｡
In the end you played with
the Mega Drive, too.
それ さっき１回言ったよ
突っ込み間違ってるよ…｡
You said that already. That's
the wrong comment.
１人 来てもらおう｡
I want one of you to come
with me. You there...
そこの女 来い｡
Come with me.
Wait, I'll go, too...
待て！ ﾎﾞｸも…｡
(お妙)みんなを お願い｡
Take care of everyone.
姉上！
Sis!
ｸｿ… どうすればいいんだ！
Crap!
What should we do? What
in the world do we do?
いったい どうすれば…｡
(九兵衛)乙姫を倒すぞ！
Let's defeat Otohime.
お妙ちゃんを救い出し
みんなの体を元に戻し➡
Let's save Otae-chan,
turn everyone back to normal
and crush Otohime's plan.
乙姫の野望を砕く｡
今 老人だらけに
なってしまったこの星で➡
Now that everyone on this
planet has become old,
we're the only ones who can do it.
それができるのは
ﾎﾞｸらしかいない！
でも どうやって…｡
But how?
Keep walking!
(亀兵士)とっとと 歩かんかい！
命だけは ご勘弁を！
Please spare my life.
今更 命乞いしたところで
もう遅いわ！
It's too late to beg for your life now!
You can regret ever becoming an enemy
of Otohime-sama in the next world!
(亀兵士)乙姫様に仇なしたこと
あの世で後悔するがいい！
Kamenashi...
亀梨…｡
おら～！
(亀梨)早く鍵を！
Quickly, grab the keys!
でかしたﾈ 亀梨！
Good work, Kamenashi!
やったね！ 神楽ちゃん｡
You did it, Kagura-chan.
What was the point of me doing that?!
(亀梨)ｵﾚの意味は!?
What are you doing?!
(亀兵士)何をしている ｷｻﾏら！
撃て！
Fire!
Out of the way, old man!
どけ じじい！
どうせ老い先 短いんだから➡
You don't have much
longer, so let me live!
ｵﾚに人生を譲れ！
You probably won't have a decent
life anyway, so let me live.
お前も どうせ この先
人生ろくなことないんじゃから➡
ﾜｼに人生 譲れ～！
桂さん！ 何やってんですか！
危ねえ!!
Katsura-san, what are
you doing?! Look out!
I'm not "Katsura," I'm "Matsu."
[Note: "Matsu" means pine tree.]
桂じゃない 松じゃ！
Even though he's an old geezer,
he really hasn't changed at all!
やっぱ ｺｲﾂ じじいになっても
何も変わんねえよ！
♪♪～
ふぅ～…｡
There's been a prison break!
(竜の子)脱獄だ～！
Kamenashi's escaped!
(亀兵士)亀梨が脱獄したぞ～！
Six of his accomplices are with
him! If you find them, kill them!
(亀兵士)ﾔﾂの仲間６人も一緒だ!!
見つけしだい 殺せ！
おいおい…
こんなんで ほんと大丈夫なのか？
Hey, hey, is this really all right?
ﾊﾞﾚたら一巻の終わりなんだけど｡
We're finished if they find us.
亀になりきれ…
不穏な動きをすれば➡
Act like a turtle.
If you make any suspicious moves,
they'll notice immediately.
すぐ気づかれるぞ｡
(長谷川)亀になりきれって➡
Act like a turtle? You're barely a turtle.
ｱﾝﾀ ほとんど亀じゃないからね！
ただのおっさんだからね！
You're just some guy.
語尾に ｺﾝﾌﾞとﾜｶﾒなどを
つけることを忘れるな！
Don't forget to add "kelp" and "seaweed"
to the end of your sentences.
お前も つけてねえだろう！
You don't do that.
Hey, what's wrong? Hang in there!
(亀兵士)
おい どうした？ しっかりしろ！
(亀兵士)出産だ～ 誰か人を呼べ！
このこ 卵 産むぞ!!
She's getting ready to lay eggs!
Someone call for help!
She's going to lay eggs!
It's all right. We'll look after
her. Sorry for the trouble.
(長谷川)あぁ いいですから…
ﾎﾞｸらが見ますんで➡
ご迷惑おかけしました！
本格的に やりすぎなんだよ！
That's too realistic!
But he said to act like a turtle.
だって亀になりきれって
言ったｱﾙよ｡
いいかげんにしろ…｡
Cut it out.
What were you planning to do if the
enemy realized who you were?!
敵に気づかれたら
どうするつもりだ？
You were gonna try it too, huh?!
[Note: Sea turtle eggs look a lot like pong pong balls.]
お前もやろうとしてたよね！
何？ そのﾋﾟﾝﾎﾟﾝ玉!?
Why else would you be holding
ping pong balls?!
いや あれをやろうと思ってな｡
Well, I got it from them.
ほらほら ﾋﾞﾋﾞったら あかんぞ！
目あけ！ 玉をよう見ろ!!
Come on. Don't be afraid.
Open your eyes!
Keep your eye on the balls!
確かに亀田！ っつうか 古いよ!!
That's definitely Kameda!
And that's so old!!
[Note: Refers to the Three Kameda Brothers, a boxing trio, who dodged ping pong balls as part of their training. "Kame" in "Kameda" means "turtle" in Japanese.]
Hey! All of you, cut it out!
おい！
いいかげんにしろよ ﾃﾒｴら!!
かつてないﾎﾞｹの量だろうが！
This is more clowning around
than you've ever done before.
I can't handle all of this by myself.
こんなもん 一人で
さばききれるわけねえだろうが！
ﾎﾞｹてなど おらんぞ 新八君｡
I'm not acting silly, Shinpachi-kun.
最終的に お前もﾒｶﾞﾄﾞﾗｲﾌﾞ
やってんじゃねえか！
In the end you played with
the Mega Drive, too.
ｵﾒｴの助けはいらねえんだよ！
I don't need your help!
(亀兵士)乙姫様 捕虜の一人を
連行してまいりました｡
Otohime-sama, I've brought
you one of the prisoners.
(乙姫)まったく
しぶとい連中よのぅ…｡
Honestly, they sure are stubborn.
They still want to defy me?
まだ わらわに逆らうというか｡
(乙姫)あきらめの悪さは
褒めてつかわそう…｡
I commend them on their persistence.
あなたが乙姫様ですか…｡
Are you Otohime-sama?
人を呼びつけておいて
顔も見せられないの…｡
You called me here and you're not
even going to show me your face?
Or is your face so ugly you
can't show anyone?
それとも人に見せられないような
顔でもしているのかしら？
(乙姫)ﾎﾎﾎ… 気の強い娘よ
悪いことをした｡
What a spirited young girl. My apologies.
反逆者に 妙齢の娘がいるとき➡
I heard there was a young
lady amongst the rebels.
ぜひ 顔が見たく
呼ばせてもらった｡
I called you here because
I wanted to see your face.
(亀梨)ｵﾚは かつて 竜宮城でも➡
I was once the Captain of Otohime's
bodyguards at Ryugu Palace.
乙姫親衛隊隊長を
務めるほどの亀だった｡
(亀梨)そう あの頃の乙姫は➡
Yes, back then Otohime was a
sparkling pearl of the ocean.
まだ燦然と輝く海の真珠だった｡
竜宮城は かつて
宇宙を股にかけて とび回る➡
Ryugu Palace was a paradise that
soared across the universe.
桃源郷だった｡
(亀梨)何者にも縛られず
何者も侵せない自由の郷｡
We weren't bound by anyone and
we didn't encroach upon anyone.
We were a free country.
Do you want to know why Ryugu Palace
has dwelled in the oceans of...
(亀梨)そんな 竜宮城がなぜ➡
今 こんな辺境の星の海に
沈んでいるか…｡
知りたいか？
this remote planet for so long?
(亀梨)はるか昔 竜宮城に
１人の青年がやってきた｡
Long ago, a young man
came to Ryugu Palace.
(亀梨)竜宮城の 使いである
亀を助けて➡
He had come to the rescue of
one of our messenger turtles.
特別に招待された
その心優しき青年を➡
That kind young man was
specially invited here.
乙姫は たいへん気に入り
厚くもてなしたという｡
Otohime grew very fond of him and
gave him a warm reception.
(亀梨)しかし 惑星国家間を越える
はるかな航程をとぶ 竜宮城と➡
But Ryugu Palace flies far distances
between planet nations.
地球の時間の流れは大きく異なる｡
And time moves very differently
than it does on Earth.
(亀梨)男が
地球へ帰ってきたとき➡
When the man returned to Earth...
彼の愛する者は
もう どこにもいなかった｡
Everyone he loved was gone.
(亀梨)
これを聞いた大楼主乙姫は➡
Upon hearing this, Otohime
became very sorrowful.
たいへん嘆き悲しみ➡
あろうことか 竜宮城を
この小さな島国の海に沈め➡
She sunk Ryugu Palace into the
seas of this small island nation
以後 とび立つことはなかった｡
and it has never left since.
(亀梨)二度と
悲劇を起こさないために➡
She discarded her position and honor
地位も名誉も
すべて捨て去ったんだ！
so this tragedy would
never happen again.
(亀梨)
心優しく気高い美しい人だった｡
She used to be so kind,
noble, and beautiful.
そんな乙姫が
変わってしまったのは➡
But little by little she changed.
いつの頃だったか…｡
((安心せえ！ わらわより若く
美しい娘であれば➡
Don't worry.
If you were a young and beautiful girl
I wasn't just going to make you old,
老いさせるだけでなく 命も
奪ってやろうと思っていたが➡
I would've taken your life.
そち程度なら
捨ておいてもいいわ｡
But since you're not, I can toss
you aside. I'm much cuter.
(乙姫)だって わらわのほうが
かわいいもん！
Huh?! Bring it on!
あぁ!? 上等だ こら！
ﾂﾗ出さんかい われ!!
Show your face! Let's settle
this fairly, you wench!
正々堂々と勝負じゃ ﾎﾞｹ!!
Huh?! You want to fight?! You
think you can beat me?!
やんのか？ こら！ わらわに
勝てると思ってんのか こら!!
(亀梨)乙姫は
齢二千を超えた頃から➡
As Otohime grew older and passed
the 2,000 year mark,
美への 執着が強くなり➡
she became more obsessed
with staying beautiful.
若返りの術を求め 方々へ
兵を走らせるようになった｡
She sent her soldiers everywhere
in search of ways to keep herself young.
(亀梨)
ﾊﾞｶげた研究に国費を費やし➡
She even used up all the public
funds on stupid research.
国は見る間に疲弊していった｡
The country quickly became bankrupt.
その過程でできたのが
何の因果か➡
And in the end we ended
up creating a device
that for some reason made people
not younger, but older.
まったく逆の効果をもつ
あの… 玉手箱Ｇ…｡
The Treasure Box G.
そう 乙姫は若返りを あきらめた｡
Otohime gave up her quest for
eternal youth and beauty.
自分ではなく周りを変えようと➡
And decided to use the box as revenge
周りを
引き下げようと考えていたんだ｡
against those who had what
she no longer did.
(亀梨)つまり この地球を
じいさん ばあさんだけにする！
In other words, she planned to turn
all the people of Earth into old geezers.
You're just a young brat, that's all!
(乙姫)ｱﾝﾀなんて
ただ若いだけでしょうが！
私だって若けりゃ  若けりゃ～！
If I was younger... If only
I was younger...
Your age isn't your only problem, tramp!
(お妙)
年齢の問題じゃないだろうが！
[To be continued...]
[Will everyone reach the palace safely?!]
[What is the secret of Ryugu that
Gintoki and the others find?]
[Otohime versus Otae. How will it end?!]
["Beauty is Like a Summer Fruit"]
[In order to split up the remaining fighting power evenly...
Kamenashi takes out his secret weapon-the Spouzer.]
[Note: Parody of Scouter from Dragon Ball.]
[Gintoki and his friends' fighting power will be revealed
next week!! Yes!! I'm getting kind of excited!]
[Note: Parody of ending
remark from Dragon Ball]